Guide to the John B. Oakes Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
John B. Oakes Papers,
1912-2005
Oakes, John B. (John Bertram), 1913-2001.
50 linear ft. (ca. 23,000 items in 113 boxes and 10 flat boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5505398
Biographical Note
John B. Oakes, journalist, editor, and environmentalist was born in Philadelphia in 1913 to George Washington Ochs-Oakes and Bertie Gans Ochs. He attended Princeton University and studied at Oxford University as a Rhodes Scholar. Following graduation, he started as a reporter on the Trenton Times and the Trenton State Gazette, and in 1937, joined the staff of the Washington Post as a police reporter, but quickly moved to covering both houses of Congress. He was drafted into the Army in 1941 and served in the Office of Strategic Services as a member of a team controlling German double agents in Europe. For this work, John Oakes received the Bronze Star, the Croix de Guerre and the Order of the British Empire. On his return to the United States in 1945, he married Margery Hartman and took a position with the New York Times, of which his uncle, Adolph Ochs, was owner and publisher. He started as a reporter and writer for the “Review of the Week” section of the Times and rose to the position of editor. In 1949, John Oakes joined the Editorial Board of the New York Times, where he became known for his interest in civil and human rights, environmentalism, and his opposition to McCarthyism and the Vietnam War. He succeeded Charles Merz as editor of the editorial page in 1961, winning the George Polk Award in 1966. He proposed and oversaw the creation of the New York Times Op-Ed page in 1970, which was the first contemporary Op-Ed page in the nation, featuring signed opinion columns designed to run opposite the paper's official (and unsigned) editorials. He was forced to leave his position as editor of the editorial page in 1976 over a dispute concerning the Times' endorsement of Daniel Patrick Moynihan in the Democratic primary; the publisher, Arthur Hayes Sulzberger, endorsed Moynihan over Oakes's objections. He continued as a contributor to the Op-Ed page into the mid-1990s, particularly focusing on environmental issues.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, speeches, scrapbooks, and printed materials of John B. Oakes, a prominent journalist and editor, who for many years editied the New York Times editorial page.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Arranged Subject Files
Series IV: Writings
Series V: Speeches and Memorials
Series VI: Printed Material
Series VII: Scrapbooks
Series VIII: Related Material
Subjects
New York Times Company.; Personal name.; Newspaper publishing.; Journalists.; Newspapers--Sections, columns, etc.; Newspaper editors.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 5-113. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
John Oakes, Gift 12/12/02 2002-2003-M16.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Acheson, Dean To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 17 Jan. 1949, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 1)
  - Adams, Ansel To John Bertram Oakes, Carmel, CA., 14 Feb. 1969, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Allen, Steve To John Bertram Oakes, Encino, CA., 10 Nov 1965, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Altschul, Arthur To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 26 April 1961-26 Jan. 1981, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) 1, t.l. ) (Box 1)
  - Altschul, Charles To John Bertram Oakes, Stanford, CT., 28 March 1984, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Altschul, Frank To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Stanford, CT., 26 April 1961-1 Nov 1973, (7t.l.s (with carbon replies and newspaper clippings) ) (Box 1)
  - Astor, Mrs. Brooke To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 20 April 1976, (1 t.l. ) (Box 1)
  - Atkinson, Brooks To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 5 May 1961-14 Feb. 1969, (4t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related letters) ) (Box 1)
  - Ball, George W. To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Princeton, NJ., 6 Oct. 1968-5 June 1992, (3t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related letters, and curriculum vitae) ) (Box 1)
  - Baker, Russell To John Bertram Oakes, New York and Washington, 9 April 1963-21 May 1979, (3 a.l.s. 24, t.l.s. (with carbon replies) 2, a.n. 1, t.n. 3, telegrams (photocopied) ) (Box 1)
  - Barzun, Jacques To John Betram Oakes, New York, 19 Nov. 1981- 8 Dec. 1981, (1 a.l.s. 1, t.l.s. (photocopy with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Begley, Louis To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 15 April 1993, (1t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Berle, Adolf A. To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 20 Jan. 1967, (1t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Berlin, Isaiah To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Oxford, 7 June 1966- 3 Jan. 1967, (1 a.l.s. 7, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related correspondence) ) (Box 1)
  - Boornstein, Daniel To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 2 Oct. 1958-7 Nov. 1983, (12 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related materials) ) (Box 1)
  - Bowles, Chester To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 21 July 1961-14 Nov. 1972, (29 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related materials) ) (Box 1)
  - Brademas, John To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, 15 Nov. 1972-25 Jan. 1990, (3 a.l.s. 4, t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Brogan, Dennis To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 4 Dec. 1963-10 Jan. [1969], (1 a.l.s. 3, t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Brown, Edmund G. (Governor of California) To John Bertram Oakes, Sacramento, CA., 21 Oct. 1966, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 1)
  - Bruce, Edmund To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, 14 Nov. 1977-21 Nov. 1977, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy with carbon reply and related materials) ) (Box 1)
  - Brzezinski, Zbigniew To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 27 April 1972, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Buckley, Jr., William F. To John Bertram Oakes and New York Times Editors, New York, 31 Oct 1974, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 1)
  - Oakes, John Bertram To Herb M., New York, [n.d.], (1 a.n. (on same sheet as above letter) ) (Box 1)
  - Bundy, McGeorge To John Oakes, New York, 7 Oct. 1969-6 Sept. 1972, (5 t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Burger, Warren E. To Warren Burger from John Bertram Oakes, New York, 7 April 1970, (1 t.l. ) (Box 1)
  - Byrd R.E. To John Bertram Oakes, Fort Wayne, ID., 2 May 1931, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 1)
  - Camfield, Cass To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 1 March 1971-15 March 1977, (5 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Carey, Hugh To John Bertram Oakes, Albany, NY, 18 July 1975, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Caro, Robert To John Bertram Oakes, [n.p.], 4 Jan 1992, (1 a.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Catledge, Turner To John Bertram Oakes, New York & [New Orleans], 4 May 1960-29 June 1970, (3 t.l.s. 9, t.l. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Clarke, James McClure To John Bertram Oakes, Asheville, NC. & Washington, 12 Nov. 1986-28 Oct. 1988, (2 a.l.s. 1, t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Clinton, William J., President U.S.A. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, 8 Feb. 1993-21 Dec. 2000, (3 t.l.s. (photocopies with related letters and replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Costa, Sergio Correa Da To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, 25 Oct. 1976-3 Nov. 1986, (1 a.l.s. 6, 7.l.s. (with carbon rplies) 1, invitation card ) (Box 1)
    [Brazilian Ambassador to the U.S.]
  - Costikyan, Edward To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 28 May 1969-18 April 1972, (8 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related correspondence, and related material) ) (Box 1)
  - Cournand, Andre To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 2 Oct. 1985, (1 1 a.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Cousins, Norman To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 10 May 1961-16 March 1972, (8 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Cowan, Louis To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 13 June 1960-24 May 1976, (1 a.l.s. (with carbon reply) 4, t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Cuomo, Mario To John Bertram Oakes, Albany, NY & New York, 14 Jan 1992-28 Oct 1992, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy with carbon reply and related material) ) (Box 1)
  - Daley, Richard To Richard Daley from John Bertram Oakes, New York, 1 Nov 1971, (1 t.l. ) (Box 1)
  - De Voto, Bernard To John Bertram Oakes, Cambridge, MA., 13 May 1955, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Dillon, Douglas To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 16 Dec 1960-18 May 1972, (5 t.l.s. (with carbon reply and related material) 1, a.n. 1, t.l. ) (Box 1)
  - Doctorow, E.L. To John Bertram Oakes, New Rochelle, NY, 22 April 1991, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Douglas, William O. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, 10 April 1962-3 Feb. 1975, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 1)
  - Eden, Anthony To John Bertram Oakes, London, 6 June 1967-7 June 1967, (2 cablegrams (photocopies with reply cables) ) (Box 1)
  - Eiseley, Loren To John Bertram Oakes, Philadelphia, 6 Nov. 1972-28 May 1976, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, a newspaper clipping, and a related letter) ) (Box 1)
  - Ford, Gerald To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, 27. Oct 1970-31 Jan. 1973, (3 t.l.s. (photocopies) ) (Box 1)
  - Frankel, Max To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 17 Sept. 1964-24 Aug. 1993, (20 a.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies) 24, t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies, related letters, newspaper clippings, draft replies, and related material) ) (Box 1)
  - Frankfurter, Justice Felix To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., [1943]-31 May 1961, (2 a.l.s. (photocopies) 6, t.l.s. (with photocopied replies and related material) 1, a.n. ) (Box 1)
  - Franks, Oliver To John Bertram Oakes, Oxford & Washington, D.C., 13 Dec. 1947-15 Nov. 1948, (3 t.l.s. (photocopies) ) (Box 1)
  - Garrison, Lloyd To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 16 Aug. 1968-9 Aug. 1985, (5 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related correspondence, and related material) ) (Box 1)
  - Gill, Brendan To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 20 June 1977, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Ginsberg, Allen To John Bertram Oakes, [New York], 23 May 1969, (1 a.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Goldberg, Rube To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 29 Sept. 1969, (1 telegram (photocopied with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Goodhart, Sir Philip To Philip Goodhart from John Bertram Oakes, New York, 28 May 1982, (1 t.l. (carbon copy) ) (Box 1)
  - Gore, Al Jr. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 27 April 1990-27 March 1993, (1 a.l.s. (photocopy) 2, t.l.s. (with carbon reply and related material) ) (Box 1)
  - Gore, Albert Sr. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 13 Feb 1962-5 June 1989, (5 t.l.s. (photocopies with related letters and material and carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Graham, Philip L. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 27 April 1961, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Hadas, Moses To Moses Hadas from John Bertram Oakes, New York, 1 June 1962-6 Sept. 1962, (3 t.l. (carbon copies) ) (Box 1)
  - Harriman, W. Averell To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, D.C., 27 June 1960-15 Sept. 1964, (1 t.l.s. 1, t.l. (with related material and carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Hentoff, Nat 1 a.l.s. (with carbon reply), New York, 26 Oct. 1970-14 Nov. 1970, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
  - Hoffman, Paul To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 11 April 1962-17 Nov. 1969, (5 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 1)
  - Horowitz, Irving Louis To John Bertram Oakes, New Brunswick, NJ, 28 Jan 1976-11 Feb. 1976, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - House, Arthur H. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 10 March 1976, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 1)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H. To John Bertram Oakes and A.O. Sulzberger, Washington, D.C., 1 April 1963-26 Nov. 1976, (30 t.l.s. (photocopies with related material and carbon replies) 1, telegram ) (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Lady Bird To John Bertram Oakes, Stonewall, TX., 21 March 1974, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy with carbon reply) ) (Box 2)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 19 Aug. 1955-18 Jan. 1969, (12 t.l.s. (photocopies with related material, related letters, and carbon replies) ) (Box 2)
  - Oakes, John Bertram To Lydon B. Johnson, New York, 16 Aug 1955, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 2)
  - Kasparov, Garry et al. To John Bertram Oakes and Margery Hartman Oakes, [n.p.], 1991, (1 Christmas cards ) (Box 2)
  - Kempton, Murray To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 16 Jan. 1970, (1 a.l.s. (with related letter) ) (Box 2)
  - Kennedy, Edward To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 4 May 1966-27 July 1979, (5 t.l.s. (photocopies with related material and carbon replies) ) (Box 2)
  - Kirk, Grayson To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 26 April 1961, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Kissinger, Henry To Henry Kissinger from John Bertram Oakes, New York, 15 Dec. 1969-7 Oct. 1974, (3 t.l. (carbon copies with related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Knopf, Alfred A. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 13 June 1953-8 Sept. 1971, (28 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related letters) 1, t.l.s. (proxy signature by secretary) ) (Box 2)
  - Knopf, Alfred A. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 23 Sept. 1971-23 April 1974, (2 a.l.s. 1, a.n.s. 25, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related letters) ) (Box 2)
  - Knopf, Alfred A. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 17 July 1974-17 Nov. 1976, (24 t.l.s. (with carbon copies, carbon replies, and related letters) ) (Box 2)
  - Knopf, Alfred A. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 24 Jan 1977-27 Oct. 1983, (5 a.l.s. (with carbon replies) 8, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related letters) ) (Box 2)
  - Koch, Edward I. To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, D.C., 3 Dec. 1969-9 March 1988, (1 a.l.s. (photocopy) 10, t.l.s. (photocopies with related material and carbon replies) ) (Box 2)
  - Kolleck, Teddy To John Bertram Oakes, Jerusalem, 15 March 1976, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Laird, Melvin To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 14 Dec. 1971, (1 1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 2)
  - Lefkowitz, Louis To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 17 Dec. 1973-13 Dec. 1974, (2 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Lehman, Herbert H. To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, D.C., 26 Aug. 1954-2 April 1963, (3 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related letters) ) (Box 2)
  - Lehman, Mrs. Herbert H. (Edith A.) To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 27 June 1974-11 July 1974, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, a related letter, and a newspaper clipping) ) (Box 2)
  - Lindbergh, Mrs. Charles A. (Anne Morrow) To John Bertram Oakes, Darien, CT, 8 July 1974, (1 t.l.s. (with related correspondence and carbon reply) ) (Box 2)
  - Lindsay, John V. To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, D.C., 18 Jan. 1960-22 Dec. 1988, (4 a.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies) 16, t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies, related letters, and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Lippman, Walter To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 26 April 1961-2 Oct. 1969, (4 t.l.s. 1, telegram ) (Box 2)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 12 June 1963-20 Feb. 1976, (3 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 2)
  - Lodge, John To John Bertram Oakes, Hartford, CT, 10 Aug. 1954, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Luce, Clare Boothe To Clare Boothe Luce from John Bertram Oakes, New York, 4 Jan. 1957, (1 t.l. (carbon copy) ) (Box 2)
  - McCarthy, Eugene To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Washington, D.C., 12 May 1972-8 June 1992, (5 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related letters, and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - McCree, Wade To John Bertram Oakes, Detroit, MI., 4 Nov. 1976-28 Jan. 1977, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related letters) ) (Box 2)
  - McDonald, Dwight To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 31 May 1963-16 June 1965, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, drafts, and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - McGhee, George To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 3 Sept. 1949-24 Jan. 1987, (1 a.l.s. (with carbon reply) 21, t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related letters, and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - McGovern, George To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 21 Jan. 1966-6 April 1990, (2 a.l.s. (photocopies) 1, telegram (photocopy) 7, t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Markel, Lester To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 21 Oct. 1953-4 Jan [1968], (2 a.l.s. (photocopies) 35, t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies) ) (Box 2)
  - Markel, Lester To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 13 Dec. 1968-7 Oct. 1976, (2 a.l.s. 13, t.l.s. (photocopies, carbon replies, and clippings) ) (Box 2)
  - Matthews, Herbert To John Bertram Oakes, New York and Washington, D.C., 26 Jan. 1962-2 Dec. 1976, (1 a.l.s. 4, a.n.s. 26, t.l.s. (photocopies, carbon replies, related letters, and clippings) ) (Box 2)
  - Meyer, Eugene To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 23 Jan 1942, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Monnet, Jean To John Bertram Oakes, Paris, 11 Feb. 1959-23 May 1966, (2 t.l.s. (carbon reply) ) (Box 2)
  - Morgenthau, Jr., Henry To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 5 April 1949, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Morgenthau, Robert To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 29 Nov. 1962-1 April 1996, (7 t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies, related letters, and clippings) ) (Box 2)
  - Moses, Robert To John Bertram Oakes, Arthur Hayes Sulzberger Jr., Robert L. Duffus, New York, 9 May 1952-1 March 1966, (7 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related letters, and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Moyers, Bill To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 27 July 1966-17 April 1973, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Moynihan, Dan To John Bertram Oakes, Cambridge, MA., 10 April 1975, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply and related correspondence) ) (Box 2)
  - Nessen, Ron (Press Secretary to the President) To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 8 Jan 1975-27 March 1975, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 2)
  - Newman, Paul To John Bertram Oakes and Margery Hartman Oakes, New York, 2 May 1986, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Nunn, Sam To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 27 March 1991, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy with related letter) ) (Box 2)
  - Oppenheimer, Robert To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 29 Sept. 1952-27 April 1961, (1 a.l.s. (with carbon reply and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Osborn, Bob To John Bertram Oakes, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 a.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Pace, Jr., Frank To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 2 June 1949-1 May 1950, (2 t.l.s. ) (Box 2)
  - Oakes, John Bertram To Frank Pace Jr. and Peggy Pace, New York, 8 Nov. 1982-1 March 1985, (2 t.l. (carbon copies) ) (Box 2)
  - Pei, I.M. To I.M. Pei from John Bertram Oakes, New York, 8 Oct. 1982, (1 t.l. (carbon copy with related letter and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Raskin, A.H. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 10 Dec. 1962-10 June 1969, (2 a.l.s. 8, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related correspondence) 1, a.n.s. 1, a.p.s. 1, telegram ) (Box 2)
  - Reagan, Ronald To John Bertram Oakes, Los Angeles, 5 March 1979, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 2)
  - Redford, Robert To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 6 Oct. 1977, (1 t.l.s. (with related letter) ) (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller, David To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 28 Oct. 1952-13 Sept. 1983, (2 a.l.s. 19, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller, John D. III To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 11 March 1966-9 July 1975, (6 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller, Lawrence To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 25 Sept. 1956-3 May 1982, (1 a.l.s. 8, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller, Gov. Nelson A. To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 9 Feb 1961-13 Sept. 1978, (1 1 a.l.s. (photocopy) 13, t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies and related letters) ) (Box 2)
  - Ruckelshaus, William D. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 22 June 1983, (1 t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 3)
  - Rumsfeld, Donald To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 8 Jan. 1975-13 Dec. 1975, (2 t.l.s. ) (Box 3)
  - Rusk, Dean To Arthur Hayes Sulzberger and John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 20 Dec. 1960-8 Sept. 1966, (2 t.l.s. (with related correspondence and newspaper clippings) ) (Box 3)
  - Russell, Bertrand To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 28 March 1963-21 Dec. 1966, (7 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related letters, and newspaper clippings) ) (Box 3)
  - Russell, John To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 30 Nov. 1986-9 June 1999, (4 a.l.s. 1, t.l.s. ) (Box 3)
  - Safire, William To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 4 Nov. 1974-2 Dec. 1974, (1 1 a.l.s. 4, t.l.s. (with related letters) ) (Box 3)
  - Salisbury, Harrison E. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 24 April 1961-5 July 1980, (2 a.l.s. 1, a.n.s. 1, a.p.s. 4, t.l.s. (with related correspondence) ) (Box 3)
  - Schlesinger, Jr., Arthur To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 31 May 1961-30 March 1989, (12 t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 3)
  - Seldes, Lee To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 4 May 1978-31 Jan. 1991, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon reply and related material) ) (Box 3)
  - Shannon, William V. To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 31 Oct. 1962-18 Sept. 1989, (9 a.l.s. 5, a.n.s. 1, a.p.s. 45, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 3)
  - Shapiro, Harold To John Bertram Oakes, Ann Arbor, MI., 14 May 1987, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 3)
  - Shriver, Jr., Donald W. To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 15 Dec. 1987, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 3)
  - Stegner, Wallace To John Bertram Oakes, Los Altos Hills, CA., 4 April 1981-9 April 1981, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 3)
  - Stevenson, Adlai To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 31 March 1961-5 June 1964, (2 t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies and related letters) ) (Box 3)
  - Stone, Shepard To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 23 Jan 1973-13 March 1986, (5 a.l.s. (with carbon replies) 9, t.l.s. (with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 3)
  - Styron, William To John Bertram Oakes, Roxbury, CT, 28 June 1974, (1 t.l.s. (with related letter) ) (Box 3)
  - Sulzberger, A.H. To John Bertram Oakes, New York & Hillandale, CT., 20 Aug. 1956-22 July 1963, (31 t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies, related letters, and clippings) 3, a.n.s. ) (Box 3)
  - Sulzberger, Mrs. A.H. (Iphigene) To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 9 Oct. 1963-14 June 1989, (4 a.l.s. 2, a.n.s. 34, t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related correspondence, and clippings) 1, telegram ) (Box 3)
  - Sulzberger, C.L. (1) To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 19 Dec. 1961-20 Dec. 1969, (23 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related correspondence, related material) 3, a.n.s. 48, telegrams (photocopies) ) (Box 3)
  - Sulzberger, C.L. (2) To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 7 Jan. 1970-23 July 1976, (5 t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related correspondence, and related material) 1, a.l. 11, telegrams ) (Box 3)
  - Thant, U To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 28 Nov. 1965-6 March 1969, (4 t.l.s. (photocopies with carbon replies and related material) ) (Box 4)
  - Thomas, Lewis To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 25 Nov. 1985, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 4)
  - Train, Russell E. To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 21 April 1970, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 4)
  - Trevor-Roper, Hugh To John Bertram Oakes, [Cambridge, MA.], 27 March 1949, (1 a.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 4)
  - Truman, Harry S. To Arthur Hayes Sulzberger, Julius Adler, and John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C. and Independence, MO., [1949?]-14 June 1960, (3 a.l.s. (photocopies with photocopy reply) 1, t.l.s. (photocopy) ) (Box 4)
  - Udall, Stewart To John Bertram Oakes, [v.p.], 9 Jan. 1961-14 Dec. 1999, (6 a.l.s. (with carbon replies) 3, a.n.s. 4, t.l.s. (with carbon replies, related correspondence, and related material) ) (Box 4)
  - Valenti, Jack To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 6 Sept. 1972, (1 t.l.s. (with carbon reply) ) (Box 4)
  - Vance, Cyrus To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 10 Dec. 1971-8 Dec. 1976, (3 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) ) (Box 4)
  - Waldheim, Kurt To John Bertram Oakes, New York, 14 June 1976, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 4)
  - Warren, Earl To John Bertram Oakes, Washington, D.C., 3 Feb. 1962, (1 t.l.s. ) (Box 4)